A Guide to the Farrar Family Papers, 1764-1998 (bulk 1880-1910)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Farrar Family Papers, 1764-1998 (bulk 1880-1910)
The Library of Virginia
43946
3 cu. ft.
Purchased from Historical Collectible Auctions, Graham, North Carolina.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchased.
Historical Information
Fernando Richard Farrar was born 7 January 1828. He was the son of Dr. Richard Eggleston Farrar and Sarah Virginia Love. He attended Randolph-Macon College, Princeton University, and the University of Virginia. Farrar practiced law in Amelia County, Virginia, maintaining his office at his home "Mohican," and was later appointed judge. He was also a gifted speaker, and toured on a lecture circuit throughout Virginia and other parts of the United States. Farrar married three times: 1) Anna Maria Austin (1826-1870) of Cumberland County, in 1853; 2) Georgia Bass, and 3) Ella G. Scott. Judge Farrar died 12 August 1898, and was buried at "Mohican."
His son, Stephen Lee Farrar, was born at "Mohican" on 12 December 1862. He attended Worsham Academy, and graduated from the University of Virginia. He was admitted to the bar in 1883, and practiced law at Amelia Court House. Farrar succeeded his father as a county judge, and then served as clerk of the circuit court (1907-1929). He married Clay Holland Griffith (1874-1949) on 25 November 1908. Following his death on 14 April 1929, she succeeded him as circuit court clerk, and served until 1936, when their son Stephen Lee Farrar, Jr. (1909-1977) succeeded her.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1764-1998, of the Farrar family of Amelia County, Virginia, including Fernando Richard Farrar (1828-1898), and his son Stephen Lee Farrar (1862-1929). Includes accounts and receipts, correspondence, clippings, estate papers, genealogical notes, information on the history of Amelia County, photographs, suit papers, scrapbook, and other items. The bulk of the collection covers the years 1880 to 1910.
The earliest correspondence deals mainly with legal and financial matters, estate settlements, and land sales. Other topics include invitations and details regarding lectures by Fernando R. Farrar, particularly for his tour in Texas and Louisiana. There are letters of sympathy to the family following the death of Lily (Farrar) Frayser (1868-1895). There is also a good deal of correspondence regarding the disposition of the family estate "Mohican" in Amelia County.
The collection contains manuscript and printed copies of lectures delivered by Fernando R. Farrar. He toured all over the South, and also traveled to Boston, where he spoke at Faneuil Hall. Some of his most popular lectures were "Johnny Reb, the Confederate," "Rip Van Winkle," and "Miss Birdie's Wedding Day." He drew large crowds at colleges, church fundraisers, town hall meetings, and Confederate reunions.
There are a substantial number of newspaper clippings regarding Amelia County and Virginia history. The genealogical files contain information on the Cocke, Cutler, Farrar, Love, Meeks, Walton, and Wright families. There are files containing information on the settlement of the estates of Fernando R. Farrar, Richard Eggleston Farrar (1800-1869), and Stephen Lee Farrar, Jr. (1909-1977). The scrapbook contains newspaper clippings, correspondence, and tributes and resolutions pertaining to the life of Fernando R. Farrar.
Contents List
- Accounts and Receipts, 1816-1838 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Accounts and Receipts, 1850-1860, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Accounts and Receipts, 1880-1884 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Accounts and Receipts, 1885-1889 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Accounts and Receipts, 1890-1895 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Accounts and Receipts, 1896-1899 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Accounts and Receipts, 1900-1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Accounts and Receipts, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Acme Mercantile Agency (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Application for the Purchase of Delinquent Land, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Address - Faneuil Hall, Boston, 17 June 1887 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Address - Laying of Church Cornerstone, 19 August 1880 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Address - Masonic Lodge, Amelia Court House, 20 December 1875 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Agreement, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Amelia County Historical Society Bulletin, 1994-1998 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Appointment to Draft Board, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Thacker Archer vs. William and Simon Archer (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Agreements (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Auction, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Austin, James M. - Obituary (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Bank Books, 1900-1925 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Benefit Show at Amelia Courthouse, August 1879 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Blanton, R. W. (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Boisseau and Coleman - Accounts, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Bonds (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Broadsides (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Cancelled Checks (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Cancelled Checks, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Cancelled Checks, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Cancelled Checks, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Cancelled Checks, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Cancelled Checks, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Cancelled Checks, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Capias, 1764 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Clerks' Fee Bills and Receipts (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Clippings (Box 2, Folder 12-15)
- Coleman, Nannie Belle (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Commercial Bank of Farmville (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Commonwealth vs R. A. Farrar (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Contract for Speaking Engagements, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Contracts 1890 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Correspondence, 1832-1869 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Correspondence, 1870-1879 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Correspondence, 1880-1889 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1890-1893 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1894 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1895 (January-May) (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1895 (June) (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1895 (July-December) (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1896-1899 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1900-1906 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1907 (January-March) (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1907 (April-December) (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1908, 1912-1919 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1920-1929 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1930-1997 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Deeds (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Dickinson vs. Farley's exors. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Election Tickets (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Envelopes (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
- Estate of Thomas Blankenship (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Estate of Fernando R. Farrar (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Estate of Richard Eggleston Farrar (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Estate of Stephen Lee Farrar, Jr. (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Family History (Box 4, Folder 10)
- S. L. Farrar et als vs. Austin et als, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Farrar, Dr. Stephen C. - Tribute and Resolutions (Box 4, Folder 12)
- "The Ferrar (Farrar) Family of England and Virginia" (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Genealogical Notes (Box 4, Folder 14-15)
- Gills, John A. (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Gravel Hill Church (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Historical Notes on Amelia County (Box 4, Folder 18-19)
- Implement Co. vs. J. W. Southall (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Jetersville Christian Church 150th Anniversary (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Johnson vs. Farrar (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Judgment Extract - Robertson vs. Booker, 1893 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Law License Applications (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Lecture - "Miss Birdie's Wedding Day" (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Lecture - "R. E. Lee" (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Lecture - "Rip Van Winkle" (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Legislative Petition - Re-Election of Judge F.R. Farrar (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Ligon Family Reunion, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- List of Fines, 1872 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- List of Speaking Engagements in Texas and Louisiana (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Lists of Witnesses and Jurors (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Mann, William Hodges (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Marriage Bonds and Licenses (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Marriage Consents (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Marriage License Applications (Box 5, Folder 17)
- McIlwaine, William B. - Address (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Memorandum Books (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Mercantile Agency - Collection Claims, 1905-1907 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Minister's Return, 1824 (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Minutes - Giles District Democrats, 1908 (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 23-24)
- Miscellaneous Speech Notes (Box 5, Folder 25)
- New Address System (Box 5, Folder 26)
- Notes re: Legal Case (Box 5, Folder 27)
- Notice of Candidacy, 1927 (Box 5, Folder 28)
- Orders for Payment or Goods (Box 5, Folder 29)
- Orders to Pay Jurors (Box 5, Folder 30)
- Pankey, J. F. - Names of Children (Box 5, Folder 31)
- Photographs (Box 5, Folder 32-33)
- Plan for Stable (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Poll, 1865 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Portraits (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Post Office - Amelia County (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Powers of Attorney (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Program Honoring John Bannister Tabb, 2 November 1969 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Promissory Notes (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Registered Letter Receipts (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Resolution - Amelia Camp C.V. No. 109, 1907 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Shelton, Theodore Petrie (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Southall, R. G. (Box 6, Folder 11)
- St. Johns-of-Hamilton Church 75th Anniversary Booklet (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Summonses, 1813, 1890 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Survey, 1838 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Sydnor Pump and Well Company (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Tax Tickets and Receipts (Box 6, Folder 16)
- The Techgram, vol. XI, no. 18, 15 June 1934 (Box 6, Folder 17)
- "Thirty-Six Hours Before Appomattox" by Chris M. Calkins, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Trains (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Tyler vs. Tyler (Box 6, Folder 20)
- UVA Class of 1887 (Box 6, Folder 21)
- Virginia Historical Society (Box 6, Folder 22)
- Walker, George E., 1898-1902 (Box 6, Folder 23)
- Warrniner, R. B. - Receipts (Box 6, Folder 24)
- Webster vs. Bugg (Box 6, Folder 25)
- Will of Ellen S. Farrar, 1890 (copy) (Box 6, Folder 26)
- Will of Joseph M. Fowlkes, 1874 (Box 6, Folder 27)
- Will of Simeon Walton, 1798 (typescript) (Box 6, Folder 28)
- Wrappers (Box 6, Folder 29)
- Book - "Amelia Family Album." Edited by Robert M. Woodcock (1985) (Box 7)
- Daguerreotypes (2) (Box 7)
- Document Holders/Wallets (2) (Box 7)
- Photograph Album (Box 7)
- "A Pocket Prayer Book and Devotional Guide" (1941) (Box 7)
- Powder Horn (Box 7)
- Scrapbook - "In Memory of Judge F. R. Farrar" (Box 7)